Guide to the Basil Champneys Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Basil Champneys correspondence
1882-1925
GEN MSS 156
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.5
(1 box)
Letters received by Basil Champneys from various correspondents including George Du Maurier, R. C. Jebb, A. C. Lyall, Hallam Tennyson, and Francis Warre Cornish. Many letters concern a dinner in 1904 for the Artists' General Benevolent Institution. Also included are manuscript pieces by Coventry Patmore, an autograph sheet, and third-party letters including items to or from Annie Wood Besant, John Fulleylove, and Brooke Foss Westcott.
Champneys, Basil, 1842-1935
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Donald S. Tuttle Book Fund and the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1995-1997.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Basil Champneys Correspondence consists principally of letters received by Basil Champneys between 1882 and 1925. Also included are letters between third parties, including three to Champneys' in-laws, the Drummonds; manuscript items by Archibald Campbell and Coventry Patmore; and an autograph sheet.
Basil Champneys (1842-1935), an author and architect in England, published the Memoirs and Correspondence of his friend Coventry Patmore in 1900. Champneys was connected to London's artistic circles, as evidenced by the letters in this collection, many of which refer to a dinner he sponsored in 1904 for the Artists' General Benevolent Institution.
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: Basil Champneys Correspondence, and Additions Since October 1995.
Architects -- Great Britain -- Archives; Artists -- Great Britain -- Archives; Architects -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Artists -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Besant, Annie, 1847-1933; Champneys, Basil, 1842-1935; Du Maurier, George, 1834-1896; Fulleylove, John, 1847-1908; Jebb, R. C. (Richard Claverhouse), 1841-1905; Lyall, Alfred C., Sir, 1835-1911; Patmore, Coventry, 1823-1896; Tennyson, Hallam Tennyson, Baron, 1852-1928; Warre Cornish, Francis, 1839-1916; Westcott, Brooke Foss, 1825-1901; Artists' General Benevolent Institution (London, England)
- BASIL CHAMPNEYS CORRESPONDENCE
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Ainger, Alfred, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Baddeley, Welbore St. Clair, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Badley, G. F., 1902 Sep 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Barnett, Samuel A. (Canon Barnett?), 1904 Aug 13 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bell, C. Moberly, 1904 Nov 22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Benson, Arthur Christopher, 1915 Jan 15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bird, Alice, 1919 Jan 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bonney, T. G. (Thomas George), 1904 Apr 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Butler, H. Montagu, 1916 Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cecil, Elgin, 1921 Mar 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Chalmers, Mackenzie Dalzell Edwin Stewart, Sir [?], 1904 Apr 11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Churton, T. T. (Theodore Townson), 1912 Nov 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Clifford, Lucy (Mrs. W. K. Clifford), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Collins, Richard Henn, 1903 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Courthope, William John, 1900, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Creighton, Louise, 1904 Dec 12 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Dailey [?], ---, [1904?] Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Dicksee, Frank (Sir Francis Bernard Dicksee), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Scope and Contents
      [fragment]
    - Du Maurier, George, 1895 Dec 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Elliot, Arthur D, 1904, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Ely, F. H., 1910 Mar 19 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Esher, Reginald Baliol Brett, Viscount, 1914 Apr 25 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Giffen, Robert, Sir, 1904 Apr 18 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Grant Duff, Mountstuart E. (Mountstuart Elphinstone), Sir, 1904 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Gwynn, Stephen Lucius, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Hanbury, Hilda, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Hawtrey, Lily, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Harraden, Beatrice, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Holland, Bernard Henry, 1904, 1925, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Holroyd, Charles, 1910 Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Islington, C. H., 1901 Jan 10 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Jackson, W. W. (William Walrond), 1898 Jun 22 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Jebb, R. C. (Richard Claverhouse), Sir, 1904 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Kennedy, W. R. [William Rann, Sir ?], 1904 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Lankester, E. Ray (Edwin Ray), Sir, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Lewis, George [George Henry Sir?], 1887 Oct 17 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Lilly, W. S. [William Samuel?], 1904 Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Lucas, E. V (Edward Verrall), 1919-20 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Lyall, A. C. (Alfred Comyn), Sir, 1904, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - McTaggart, J. Ellis (John McTaggart Ellis), 1907 Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Martin, Theodore, [1904] Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Morris, Lewis, Sir, 1904 Apr 14 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Murray, John, 1904 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Newbolt, Henry John, Sir, 1915, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Onslow Ford, E., 1893 Jan 19 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Peile, John, 1901 Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Phelps, L. R., 1914 Jul 14 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Pollock, F. [Frederick, Sir?], 1904 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Prothero, G. W. (George Walter), 1904 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Read, C. H., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Russell, Agatha, 1916 Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Russell, George William ("A. E."), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Rhoades, James, 1904 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Richmond, W. B. (William Blake), Sir, 1900 Aug 3 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Selborne, [William Waldegrave Palmer, Earl of ?], 1918 Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Sichel, W. [Walter Sydney ?], 1904 Apr 21 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Storey, George Adolphus, 1901 Jul 15 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Strachey, John St. Loe, 1904 Apr 18 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Temple, Richard, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Tennyson, Hallam Tennyson, Baron, 1918 Apr 30 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Thornycroft, William Hamo, Sir, 1900 Nov 2 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Trevelyan, George Otto, Sir, 1904 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - University of Cambridge, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Vernon, William Warren, 1904 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Wallace, D. M., 1904 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Ward, Josephine Mary (Hope-Scott), 1910-1921 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Warre Cornish, Francis, 1904 Jul 4 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Welldon, J. E. C. (James Edward Cowell), [1904] (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - White, W. H. [William Hale ?], 1904 Apr 7 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Winton, Edward, 1919 Jul 5 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Winston, Randall [?], 1899 Dec 12 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Unidentified, 1884-1914 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Draft of letter to "Talbot", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Third-Party Correspondence
    - [Abbey, Edwin Austin?] to "Ford", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - [Alemand?, L---] to Lester Drummond, 1915 Dec 12 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Curzon, --- to Francis Champneys, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Dunelm, J. B., letter of recommendation for Basil Champneys, 1882 Jan 27 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Dyke, W. Hart to Annie Wood Besant, 1904 Nov 30 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Edward VII, King of Great Britain to E. S. Tregoning, 1904 Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Harmcliffe, W. to Rev. Canon Lee, 1882 Jan 27 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - "Herbrand" to "Agatha" (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Horn [?], Frank to E. Onslow Ford, 1885 Mar 12 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Linton, J. O. to John Fulleylove, 1899 Oct 14 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Maude, Cyril to Mr. Davies, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Maude, Winifred to Mrs. Davies, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Sewell, J. S. to "Bourne", 1902 Apr 15 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Waller, Lewis to Mr. Drummond, 1900 Nov 5 (Box 1, Folder 87)
      Includes photograph of LW
    - Westcott, Brooke Foss, letter of recommendation for Basil Champneys, 1882 Jan 27 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Unidentified to Chanoine Cardyn, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Unidentified to A. C. Champneys, 1899 Nov 14 (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Unidentified to Cecily Champneys, 1898 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Unidentified to Mrs. Davies, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - Unidentified to Mr. Drummond (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - Unidentified to B. W. Martin, 1902 Feb 3 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Writings
    - Campbell, Archibald: Fragment of poem, holograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 95)
    - Patmore, Coventry Kersey Dighton: "Let be" and "Farewell," holograph, corrected and signed (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Personal Papers
    - Autograph sheet, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 97)
- ADDITIONS SINCE OCTOBER 1995
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Benson, Arthur Christopher, 1906 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 98)
    - De Vere, Aubrey, 1901 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 99)
    - Garnett, Richard, 1898 Oct 15 (Box 1, Folder 100)
    - Henley, William Ernest, 1900 Feb 8 (Box 1, Folder 101)
    - Meynell, Alice, n.y. Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 102)
    - Parry, C. Hubert H., 1904 Apr 13 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Third-Party Correspondence
    - De Vere, Aubrey to Mrs. Coventry Patmore, 1899 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 104)
    - Dennis, John to Mrs. Coventry Patmore, 1899 Nov 29 (Box 1, Folder 105)
    - Sutton, H. S. to Mrs. Coventry Patmore, 1899 Nov 29 (Box 1, Folder 106)